Three years ago, I traveled to the Central African Republic to report on its ongoing war. I'd heard warnings of massacres in the country's jungles and deserts, but no one could locate these massacres or tell me who was killed, or when. I drove into this war with little information. I witnessed scenes that were tragic and unreal, and only at the end did I realize that I had witnessed the slow preparation of ethnic cleansing. The Central African Republic is a country of about five million people the size of Texas in the center of Africa. The country has known chronic violence since French colonial rule ended in 1960. The war I reported on was between the minority Muslim government, called the Seleka, and citizen militias, mostly Christian, called the anti-balaka. The first sign of the impending cleansing was the breakdown of trust within communities. Three days after I arrived in the country, I watched the small city of Gaga be abandoned. A battle was about to break out. And to save themselves, many people were working as government spies, identifying friends and neighbors to be killed. Cities and towns, any place with humans, had become unsafe. So people moved to the jungle. I felt strangely isolated as pigs and livestock moved into the empty homes. In a war zone, you know that you are near the killing when people have left. The war moved across the jungle and reached Gaga, and I was surrounded by the thunder of bombs.
Hace tres años viajé a la República Centroafricana para informar sobre la guerra en curso. Había oído advertencias de genocidios en las selvas y desiertos del país, pero nadie podía saber donde ocurrían estos genocidios o decirme a quién habían asesinado o cuándo. Irrumpí en la guerra con poca información. Presencié escenas trágicas e irreales, y al final, pude darme cuenta que fui testigo del minucioso plan de limpieza étnica. La República Centroafricana es un país de alrededor de 5 millones de personas, tan enorme como Texas, en el centro de África. El país sufría de grave violencia desde la caída de la colonia francesa en 1960. La guerra de la que yo informé era entre el gobierno minoritario musulmán, llamados los Seleka, y las milicias civiles, en su mayoría cristiana, llamada los anti-balaka. La primera señal de limpieza inminente era la crisis de confianza dentro de las comunidades. Tres días después de mi llegada al país, Vi que la pequeña ciudad estaba abandonada. Una guerra iba a estallar. Para poder salvarse, muchos se convirtieron en espías del gobierno, entregando a amigos y vecinos para matarlos. Las ciudades y aldeas, cualquier lugar donde hubiera humanos era ya inseguro. Así que, la gente se mudó a la selva. Me sentí muy aislado cuando los cerdos y el ganado entraban a las casas vacías. En una zona de guerra, sabes que estás cerca de la muerte cuando la gente ya no está. La guerra se movía hacia la selva llegando hasta Gaga. El estruendo de bombas me rodeaba.
Government forces drove into the jungle to attack a town sheltering a militia. I rode on motorcycle for hours, crossing jungle streams and tall elephant grass, but I only got to the town after the government had burned it and its people were gone. To see if I could speak to someone, I shouted out that I was a friend, that I would not hurt them. A woman in a red shirt ran out of the forest. Others cautiously emerged from the trees and asked, "Est-ce les gens savent?" "Do people know?" The question surprised me. Their children were hungry and sick, but they didn't ask for food or medicine. They asked me, "Do people know what is happening to us?" I felt helpless as I wrote down their question. And I became determined that this moment in their lives should not be forgotten. In bearing witness to their crisis, I felt a small communion with these people.
El gobierno fue a la selva para atacar a las milicias escondidas en la ciudad. Conduje una moto por horas, atravesando la selva y el alto pasto elefante. Sin embargo, cuando llegué a la aldea, el gobierno ya la había incendiado y su gente había huido. Para ver si había alguien, tuve que gritar que era un amigo y que no lastimaría a nadie. Una mujer con camiseta roja salió corriendo del bosque. Otros salieron precavidamente de los árboles y preguntaron: "Est-ce que les gens savent?" ¿La gente sabe? La pregunta me sorprendió. Sus hijos tenían hambre y estaban enfermos, pero no pidieron alimentos ni medicamentos. Me preguntaron: ¿La gente sabe lo que nos ocurre? Me sentí impotente al anotar su pregunta. Y decidí entonces que este momento en sus vidas debería recordarse. Al relatar su desgracia, sentí cierta conexión con esta gente.
From far away, this war had felt like a footnote in world news. As a witness, the war felt like history unfolding. The government denied that it was committing any violence, but I continually drove through towns where people described government massacres from a day or a week before. I felt overwhelmed and tried to calm myself. As I reported on these massacres, I bought and ate little sweets, seeking the familiar comfort of their taste. Central Africans ate these sweets to ease their hunger, leaving a trail of thousands of plastic wrappers as they fled. On the few radio stations still operating in the country, I mostly heard pop music. As the war mounted, we received less information about the massacres. It became easier to feel a sense of normalcy. I witnessed the effect of this missing information. Two weeks later, I slowly and anxiously drove into an isolated militia headquarters, a town called PK100. Here, Christian fighters told me that all Muslims were foreigners, evil and allied with the government. They likened Muslims to animals. Without neutral observers or media to counter this absurd narrative, it became the single narrative in these camps. The militias began to hunt down Muslims, and emptied the capital, Bangui, of nearly 140,000 Muslims
Desde lejos, muchas noticias del mundo no dejaban de hablar de esta guerra. Como testigo, la guerra era como desarrollar una historia. El gobierno negó haber cometido algún acto de violencia. No obstante, yo seguido iba a las aldeas donde la gente describía los genocidios del gobierno de un día o semana antes. Me sentía agobiado e intentaba calmarme. Cuando informé de estas matanzas, compraba y comía golosinas, procurando que fueran de su agrado. los centroafricanos comían estos dulces para mitigar el hambre, dejando rastro de las miles de envolturas de plástico mientras huían. En algunas de las estaciones de radio que seguían operando en el país, escuchaba casi siempre música pop. A medida que la guerra avanzaba, recibíamos menos información de los asesinatos. Fue más fácil sentirse normal ante esto. Presencié los efectos de la falta de información. Dos semanas más tarde, ingresé, lenta y nerviosamente, a un cuartel general abandonado, a una aldea llamada PK100. En este lugar, los luchadores cristianos me contaron que todos los musulmanes eran extranjeros, malvados y que estaban aliados con el gobierno. Comparaban a los musulmanes con animales. Por no haber observadores neutrales o medios informativos que se opusieran a esta historia absurda, esta fue la única correcta en los campos. El ejército comenzó a capturar a los musulmanes, y vació la capital, Bangui, con un estimado de 140 000 musulmanes,
in just a few months. Most of the killing and fleeing of Muslims went unrecorded by witnesses. I'm telling you about my reporting in the Central African Republic, but I still ask myself why I went there. Why put myself at risk? I do this work because I feel that ignored people in all our communities tell us something important about who we are.
en solo pocos meses. Los testigos no registraron la mayoría de los asesinatos y fugas musulmanes. Les relato mi informe que hice en la República Centroafricana. Sin embargo, aún me cuestiono el porqué estuve ahí. ¿Por qué exponerme? Trabajo en esto porque siento que la gente que es ignorada en nuestras comunidades nos revela algo importante sobre quiénes somos.
When information is missing, people have the power to manipulate reality. Without witnesses, we would believe that those thousands of massacred people are still alive, that those hundreds of burned homes are still standing. A war zone can pass for a mostly peaceful place when no one is watching. And a witness can become precious, and their gaze most necessary, when violence passes silently,
Cuando falta la información, las personas pueden manipular la realidad. Sin testigos, seguiríamos creyendo que esas miles de personas asesinadas están vivas... y que esos cientos de hogares quemados siguen ahí. Una zona de guerra puede considerarse un lugar pacífico cuando nadie mira. Y un testigo puede ser valioso, y su mirada más que necesaria, cuando la violencia es silenciosa,
unseen and unheard. Thank you. (Applause)
inadvertida e inaudita. Gracias. (Aplausos)